hey it's Brett contas here in uh Brett
contas strength and conditioning AKA
Brett's garage um I have a post on
strengthcoach.com right now it's a
really good post if you're a member I
recommend you go uh read through it but
basically I'm not trying to get people
to start doing crunches anymore I'm just
kind of questioning um Dr Stuart Mill's
research um not so much questioning as
research but trying to offer an
explanation as to why in McGill's Labs
he shows that um 18,000 to 25,000
low-load flexion extension Cycles in the
lumbar spine lead to disc
herniations when there's people who have
performed millions of crunches
throughout their lives and have not
herniated their disc so um I just want
to show you um basically if you've got
the lumbar spine when it es and
extends um the discs the nuclei within
the disc picture this is a disc there's
nuclei in the middle and it will migrate
depending on you know whether you're
flexing extending and when you Flex the
lumbar spine like
this it migrates posteriorly and pushes
up against the anulus of the disc up
against the um and it it works its way
through the laminate through the
different um anulus f so that can lead
to discarnation so pretty much the
strength training industry has said you
know avoid lumbar flexion don't do these
exercise there's better exercises
anyway and I'm I have a different line
of thought I kind of think anything's
good as long as it doesn't hurt you it's
good to strengthen almost any range of
motion and in some sports like Jiu-Jitsu
having really strong rectus abdominis
can help you out
so um for in that instance you know if
you do heavy weighted crunch
and they weren't bad for your lumbar
spine then I say go ahead and do them
the question is whether or not they're
bad for your lumbar spine if you read
Mill's stuff you'd say of course it's
bad you know flexing extending but Migel
has stated that it's end range flexing
in extension there's some wiggle room in
there if here's your disc and the nuclei
is just going in this neutral zone then
it's not that big of a deal it's not
creating damage so how do you know if
you're staying in a safe neutral zone
well well in a crunch you would want to
make sure that most of see right here
I'm going to keep my lumbar spine it's
not moving my lumbar spine is not moving
right now I've got some wiggle room so
if you crunch now I'll I'll go all at
the lumbar spine see that so there's
there's difference there's lumbar range
of motion and thoracic range of motion
so I'm going to show you it with a
crunch here would be like I'm not even
moving my lumbar spine there's still a
gap here in
my like I'm not even really moving
much at my lumbar vertebrae it's mostly
all thoracic now if I actually put my
feet up and like I mean it's really hard
for me to move in my lumbar spine still
this here is all th mostly all thoracic
range of motion so if I wanted to do
lumbar range of motion I kind of have to
like go like this it's really hard to
get that lumbar spine to flex up so
that's my explanation as to why there's
um some contrast between McGill's
research and what's going on in the real
world I don't think we're getting that
end range flexion when we crunch however
if you're someone who has back pain or
someone who sits all day long you would
not want to do these crunches what's the
point if you're not you know
there there are safer exercises planks
side planks P off presses and work on
those cuz you need core stability but as
far as core strength goes I always used
to do heavy uh dumbbell crunches and I
would
put you
know 100 lb on
my on myself like this
and just crunch
up like that I used to be really really
strong at these this is only 100 lb and
I just struggled to get a few but at one
point I could
do 160 lbs for 20 reps then I found out
crunching is bad for you I stopped doing
them now I really um I've kind of dived
into the research and I don't think it's
as bad for you so um that rectus ABD
dominant strength when when I would have
people in Jiu-Jitsu when I used to
practice Jiu-Jitsu I would have people
come on top of me and I could kind of
push them up based on my rectus abdomin
stength I could push them off of me so
there is wiggle
room it matters where your where the
flexion is coming from so thoracic
flexion not that bad lumbar flexion very
bad also with deadlifts you watch people
you know ideal deadlift form would be
like this keeping the the thoracic and
lumbar spine in in neutral or even
slightly arched when the weight gets
heavy you will watch people especially
power lifters they'll round the upper
back like this now you notice I'm
rounding my upper back but still keeping
the lumbar spine pretty much locked up
not much motion there so again here's
how much range of motion I can get in my
thoracic and in my thoracic spine with
flexion so here's what a good deadlift
looks like here's what a lot of
powerlifters do right here and if you
watch my lumbar
spine is not moving it's just you know
my lumbar spine stays there so you got
some wiggle room so that helps
explain why some people aren't hurting
themselves when they deadlift when they
round their upper back not their lower
back so I guess all I'm saying is just
trying and pay attention to where the
flexion is coming from thoracic flexion
is okay um lumbar flexion is not okay
there is a little bit of wiggle room in
there um there's more kind of functional
um exercises for a standing position
standing Sports the the rectus abdominus
kind of transfers energy is a
transmitter not a producer of power so
you also want to do things like you know
like cable chops and uh or cable lifts
cable chops and things like that
landmines and different things where
you're transferring energy but in some
sports such as gymnastics you know you
would want to do lots of different
hanging leg raise type movements to
strengthen that rectus abdominis some
sports where you're hanging from a bar
where you're lying on the ground the
rectus the Dominus needs to have
concentric strength and it's not just a
transmitter of energy it's an actual
producer of power so in in that
situation you would want power so again
not trying to Advocate crunches not
trying to bring crunches back I'm just
kind of questioning why is there such a
gap you know people doing millions of
crunches and not hurting their Lumar
spine versus McGill's research in the
lab that shows 18 to 25,000 flexion
Cycles um and under heavy load only
5,000 flexion Cycles will produce
herniation so um anyway I hope you
enjoyed the video um be sure to check
out my blog at www. bre.com or brett.
wordpress.com thanks a lot